Now previously, we have talked about the
difference
between fluid statics and fluid dynamics.
And in this video, we will be going more
in
depth of fluid statics.
For fluid statics, it's mostly about just
buoyant
forces and buoyancy. So let's introduce
you
to buoyant forces. Obviously, you have
heard
of what buoyancy is.
If you haven't, then that might be an
issue.
But you have heard the general term of
what
buoyancy is. For example, if you hold a
ball
underwater, a beach ball underwater, let's
say,
it's going to rise up to the top.
If you swim, if you hold a pole buoy or a
paddleboard
underwater, it's also going to rise to the
top.
And that is buoyancy.
So buoyancy is the force acting on an
object
as a result from displacing
a fluid, displacing a fluid's volume.
Because when you're putting it in the
water,
it's going to displace some of the volume.
And we will get into that later. Force
acting
on an object, salt.
Okay, so what is volume displacement?
Well, it's basically like, for example, if
you're
in a bathtub, and the water is filled to
the
brim at the bathtub. If you go in the
bathtub,
the water is not going to stay filled in
the
brim. Some of the water is going to leak
and
overflow out of the hot tub.
Once you get in. And that is the water
displaced.
The volume of the water displaced,
however,
is the exact same amount of the volume
that
your body goes in the water.
That's pretty straightforward. If you put,
if
you place a block of, let's say, five,
with
a volume of five liters inside a tube, the
volume
of the water going out would also be five
liters.
And now let's get into the formula of
buoyant
force. So the buoyant forces formula is,
oh,
before that, why do some objects sink
while
some objects don't? Well, you guys have
hopefully
learned of dynamics. And so you know that
dynamics,
there's obviously free body diagrams.
And in this case, there are two forces
acting
on an object. There will be two forces
on this. For example, if you have a rock,
there
will be the buoyant force and the force of
gravity.
And if the force of gravity is higher than
the
buoyant force, then the net force will be
acting
down, which will ultimately be making it
go
down. Or if you want it formula-wise, it
would
be F net equals, let's say, positive would
be
up. It would be the buoyant force
subtracted
by the gravity force. And if F net is
negative,
well, it's going to sink. The formula for
the
buoyant force depends on two things, the
density
of the fluid and also the
volume displaced.
And the reason I say volume displaced, not
the
volume of the object, is, for example, if
you
have an object here, the volume of this
object
is not the same as the volume displaced.
The volume displaced is only the volume of
the
object that is below the water level.
And the buoyant force uses these by, let's
say,
it's the same thing as the density of the
fluid,
rho fluid, times the acceleration of
gravity,
on Earth it's 9.81, as you know, and the
volume
displaced. The volume displaced, we'll
just
call it V displaced. And
that would be the buoyant force.
Let's have an example question over here,
where
we see whether an object sinks or floats.
Let's say we have a ball over here, or a
sphere
in this case, whose radius is 5 metres.
And it has a mass of, let's say, 10
kilograms. So radius is 5 metres, and mass
is
10 kilograms. And let's pretend the liquid
water. And
from this information, we actually can
just
directly calculate whether it sinks or
not.
And yeah, a pole buoyant doesn't float
because
it's made of that material. It depends
entirely
on only the mass of whatever your object
is,
and the density, not the material.
I mean, the material could affect the
mass,
but it's mostly on the mass. And the
volume
displaced. That's why ships don't sink,
because
it displaces a large amount of volume.
So even if it's really, really heavy, and
it's
made of metal, it still does not sink.
Yeah,
so we have to calculate the net force.
Let's draw a free-body diagram. Oops, what
happened
there? Let's draw a free-body diagram.
You have the buoyant force and the
gravity.
We do not know the magnitude, so I'll keep
them
about equal lengths. So f net is given by
the,
like I said, the buoyant force minus the
gravity,
so fb minus fg.
And what is the buoyant force? Well, the
buoyant
force, as we found over here, is the
density
of the fluid times whatever.
So the density of water. The density of
water
is a constant, and it's 1000 kilograms per
metres cubed.
And this you should know.
So buoyant force is density of water times
acceleration
of gravity times volume displaced, which
is,
for a sphere, it's 4 over 3 pi r cubed
minus
force of gravity is just mass times
gravity.
So density of water, we can plug that in.
1000. For simplicity, I'll just not write
the
units. Times 9.81 times 4
over 3 pi r cubed.
Sorry, 4 over 3 pi times 5 cubed, which is
125, minus 10 times 9.81.
Once you calculate it, let me just get my
calculator
out. Give me a sec.
All right, so the value I got for this one
is
a really big number.
And I'm just going to ignore sig figs for
simplicity
sake. Minus about 98.1 newtons.
And obviously, this is very theoretical.
I just made these unit values on the spot.
But as you can see, in this case, the
buoyant
force way exceeds the gravitational force,
which
means if you submerge this, this thing is
going
to have a net force of a lot, a really,
really
big net force, and it's just going to
start
accelerating. But this is, like I said,
probably
not possible. I just made these numbers on
the
spot. It's 89.
And yeah, that's a basic calculation of
buoyancy
and the introduction of buoyancy.
Thank you for listening.